Key Concepts. Here are the meanings
of some key words and concepts:
"Don't compromise yourself. You are all
you've got." Janis Joplin
Ethics. The process of determining right
and wrong conduct. The discipline dealing
with what is good and bad
and with moral duty and obligations
Ethical Behaviour. Behaviour that conforms to
accepted standards of conduct
Ethical Reasoning. The process of sorting
out the principles that help determine
what is ethical when faced with
an ethical dilemma
Ethical System. A specific formula for
distinguishing right from wrong
Unethical. An action or conduct which
violates the principles of one or
more ethical systems, or which is
counter to an accepted ethical value,
such as honesty
Non-ethical Considerations. Powerful human motivations that
are not based on right or
wrong, but on considerations of survival
and well-being, such as health, security,
love, wealth, or selfesteem
Ethical Dilemma. This is an ethical
problem in which the ethical choice
involves ignoring a powerful non-ethical consideration.
Ethical Alarms. “Ethics alarms are the
feelings in your gut, the twinges
in your conscience, and the sense
of caution in your brain when
situations involving choices of right and
wrong are beginning to develop, fast
approaching, or unavoidable.” The better your
ethics alarm is working and the
sooner your alarm goes off the
more likely you are to do
the right thing, or at least
use good ethical reasoning to decide
what to do.
The Importance of Ethical Conduct in
Business. The field of business ethics
often overlaps and informs ethical decision
making for engineers. your business dealings.
The company‟s reputation is in your
hands and it therefore depends on
you to do the right thing
in the best interests of the
organization. High standards in business conduct
will go a long way to
meriting the confidence and support of
your clients and employers. While business
practices may change over time, our
commitment to the highest standards of
integrity should remain constant and unblemished.
Conducting business ethically is critical to
success in the marketplace. It means
more than obeying the law; it
means that high standards of integrity
must underlie every activity we undertake.
It is up to the engineer
to apply these guidelines to the
best of their ability in their
own individual situation.
Professional Ethics. In life our behavior
is governed by different norm systems.
The word NORM comes from Latin
“NORMA”= yardstick. Norms dictate what we
“ought” or “ought not” to do.
The norm systems governing the behaviour
of a professional are:
Individual morality. Refers to individual values
of a specific person and what
they believe to be right. Individual
morality is influenced by how a
person was raised. It is their
personal value system. The sanction for
disobeying one‟s individual morality is a
guilty conscience.
Positive morality. This set of norms
represents what is considered “right” in
society at a particular time. The
sanction for failure to obey positive
morality is social sanction.
Law (Legal Norms). Laws protect society
and prevent anarchy by regulating behavior.
Public Law. also referred to as
criminal law: between the state and
individual.
Private Law. also referred to as
contractual law and focuses on the
relationship between persons.